<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE foo [
    <!ENTITY uuml "&#252;">
    <!ENTITY lt "&#060;">
    <!ENTITY gt "&#062;">
]>

<document>
 
 <title>A DHCP controlled Firewall System - Version 1</title>
 
 <author>
  <name>Oliver Baltzer</name>
  <email>ob@racon.net</email>
 </author>
 
 <date>2002-03-06</date>
 
 <meta>
 
  <description>
   This specification of the dhcp-fw system describes which functionality
   is provided by the different components of the system and how does these
   components work together. There is also a short description of how the
   system can be configured.
  </description>
  
  <keywords>
   firewall dhcp-fw dhcp fw control authorisation host
   client security network
  </keywords>
 
 </meta>
 
 <content>
  <toc/> 
  
  <!-- 
    **********************************************
    *              Introduction                  *
    **********************************************
  -->
  
  <section heading="Introduction"> 
   <paragraph>
    Since the beginnings of computer networking it was never possible to
    think about it without thinking about security issues. During the last
    years the traditional security techniques became more and more
    insecure and were not able to sustain the growing criminal potential
    in the  Internet anymore. One new attempt to reduce criminal activity
    on or to the network and to keep track of them are Firewalls in the
    general meaning of a configuration element which is able to control
    and to record network activities. The most common use of a Firewall is
    this as a packet filter which allows or blocks data packages according
    to their origin, destination or application they address. These
    decision-making points are usually known as rules. Most of the time
    these rules are defined statically and they are usually used to
    protect one or more private networks from one or more public networks.
    Here you have at least one trusted network on one side of the firewall
    which is a private network in that case. You assume that you have a
    negligible criminal potential in this network and you only have to
    care about any potential criminal  activity from the public network.
    This approach works fine as long as you have full control about your
    private network, but if you like to provide a semi-public network
    access where everybody can access the physical network with her own
    computer and the potential for criminal activities is relatively high
    in that area, than you will need a solution which protects all
    networks from each other. In such an environment it is also not
    possible to use static rules anymore, because the network topology is
    changing very often and is not under full control by you.
   </paragraph>
   <paragraph>
    The following work will introduce you to a Firewall system which is
    flexible enough to adapt to the changing network topology dynamically
    and also tries to keep control of the accesses to the network.
   </paragraph>
   <paragraph>
    The system was developed within the scope of a course in System
    Administration at the  
    <link href="http://www.f1.fhtw-berlin.de/">Fachhochschule f&uuml;r
    Technik und Wirtschaft</link> in Berlin/Germany. 
    The environment it is intended to use in is a computer lab
    administrated by students where it is possible to attach one's own
    laptop to the network of the university to access the campus network
    and the Internet. The picture shows the structure of the network in
    this lab.
    <image href="before.png" title="The original structure of the network"/>
    The problem in that environment is, that the
    students who maintaining the computer lab, are not always available to
    control who is attaching her laptop to the network and what she is
    doing. On the other hand the people using these facilities are also
    students with strong knowledge of networking systems and how to
    corrupt them for their own use.  Accordingly the goal of the system is
    to control the access to the network and make it difficult for the
    user to abuse it for illegal use.
   </paragraph>
  </section>

  <!-- 
    **********************************************
    *          Keeping the Structure             *
    **********************************************
  -->

  <section heading="Keeping the Structure">
   <paragraph>
    The main issue while developing the system was that it should fit into
    a network without changing anything on the existing structure. The
    goal was to keep all network equipment and IP addresses as they are
    and the view on the network from the point of other networks should
    also stay the same. There are a few possibilities to realize this
    approach partly. The obvious one is Network Address Translation (NAT)
    where all local host addresses are mapped to their corresponding ones
    used in the external network. Usually Network Address Translation is
    handled by a router combined with a Firewall. The problem here is,
    that all machines in the local network have to be reconfigured with a
    new host address and that changes the structure of the network and its
    internal view. The next possibility is to use a private network
    between the Firewall and the main router for the network. But that
    means that the router have to be reconfigured which is not included in
    our administration domain. Finally the best choice for that case is
    to use an Ethernet bridge combined with the functionality of a
    Firewall. One of the biggest advantages of the Ethernet bridge is that
    it can operate completely transparent for the overlaying network
    protocols, for example the Internet Protocol (IP). It will just
    separates two Ethernet segments from each other without touching the
    protocol information in layers above the Ethernet layer. So you can
    use the same network addresses on both sides of the Ethernet bridge
    and the bridge is not visible for any network protocols above the
    Ethernet protocol. The following picture shows the network configuration after
    adding the bridge to the network.
    <image href="after.png" title="The network structure with the Firewall."/>
   </paragraph>
  </section>
  
  <!-- 
    **********************************************
    *          Authenticate a User               *
    **********************************************
  -->
  
  <section heading="Authenticate a User">
   <paragraph>
    To have full control on who is accessing the network, it is
    necessary to authenticate each single user who wants to access the
    network with her own machine. The machine of a user can be identified
    by its unique Ethernet MAC address. Now, to get access to the network with
    one's own machine the user has to register the MAC address of that
    machine. Only registered machines will get a host (IP) address in the
    network and will be not blocked by the firewall. 
    The IP address of a known machine will be served by a DHCP server.
    The DHCP server keeps track of all handed out IP addresses (leases)
    in a file (lease file). This file is observed by a Firewall
    Registration Daemon which adjusts the Firewall rules according to the
    content of the lease file. Sometimes one user hase more privileges in a
    network than another one, or sometimes one machine is allowed to
    provide a service and the others not. Here you need a distinction
    between the privileges of each machine and default privileges if one
    machine does not get special privileges.
   </paragraph>
  </section>

  <!-- 
    **********************************************
    *          System Requirements               *
    **********************************************
  -->
  
  <section heading="System Requirements">
   <paragraph>
    Bridges are widely used and as multiport bridges commonly known as
    (Ethernet-) switches, but most of them do not support packet filtering
    or even can operate on higher protocol layers than the network protocol
    layer. There are only a few commercial products available which can do packet
    filtering in bridging mode, but these are very expensive and not
    flexible enough to fulfil our needs. Another way is to build an own
    system using standard PC components. For a 100Mbps Ethernet network
    (100Base-T) you will need at least a 300 MHz CPU system and two network
    cards. Assuming that the system should run uninterrupted you should make
    sure that all components are working together without exceptions and
    fit together perfectly. You should also make sure that moving parts are
    of high quality to prevent a failure and all components should be supported
    by the software you want to use. For example, some network cards do not
    work correctly with Linux and they just stop working after a certain
    amount of time.
   </paragraph>
   <paragraph>
    The system must provide
    Ethernet-bridging, packet filtering and must be flexible enough for
    own extensions. Because of bridging together with packet filtering is not a
    commonly used technique, not a lot operating systems support it. Two
    systems from the open source section which can do that are Linux and FreeBSD. 
    The system described in this document is based on Linux but it should
    work similary on FreeBSD.
   </paragraph>
  </section> 
  
  <!-- 
    **********************************************
    *             Setup the System               *
    **********************************************
  -->

  <section heading="Setup the System">
   <paragraph>
    First of all there is to say that going through the installation
    process of the system it not trivial. You should bring some experiences
    in configuring and compiling a Linux kernel with you and you should
    also know how to apply patches to software source code. 
   </paragraph>
   
   <!-- 
     **********************************************
     *           Preparing the Kernel             *
     **********************************************
   -->
   
   <section heading="Preparing the Linux Kernel and the System Tools">
    <paragraph>
     Originally the Linux kernel
     supports bridging of network interfaces, but does not support packet
     filtering on these at the same time. So it is necessary to apply a
     patch to the kernel which enables packet filtering on a bridge device.
     The patch for the latest kernel version can be obtained from 
     <link href="http://bridge.sf.net/">http://bridge.sf.net/</link>. To
     install hte patch you have to change into the root directory of the
     kernel source tree. Usually this is <code>/usr/src/linux</code>. Here
     you need to call:
     <codeblock># patch -p1 &lt; /path/to/bridge-nf-x.x.x-against-y.y.y.diff</codeblock>
     where <code>x.x.x</code> is the version number of the Bridge-Netfilter
     patch and <code>y.y.y</code> is the version of the kernel you want to
     apply the patch to.
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph>
     If you have applied the bridge-nf patch to the kernel you need to add
     another patch to the kernel source before you can configure and
     compile it. This patch will enable the matching of MAC destination
     addresses in the Netfilter code of the kernel. The default Linux
     kernel only supports the matching of MAC source addresses, but the
     Firewall Registration Daemon uses the MAC addresses of the local
     hosts to determine whether or not a network package can pass the
     Firewall and that is why the matching must be bidirectional. The patch
     to enable the matching of MAC destination addresses can be found at 
     <link href="http://www.racon.net/projects/bridge-fw/">http://www.racon.net/projects/bridge-fw/</link>. 
     You should apply it to the Linux kernel source in the same way 
     you did with the bridge-nf patch. In the root directory of the kernel
     source tree just call:
     <codeblock># patch -p1 &lt; /path/to/mac_dst_match-x.x.x-against-y.y.y.diff</codeblock>
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph>
     Now you should be able to configure your kernel, compile and install
     it including all modules you have created. During the configuration
     make sure you select "netfilter (firewalling) support" in the bridge
     section of the configuration (hint: you have to enable netfilter
     first) otherwise the Firewall will not work.
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph>
     To make use of the new features in the Netfilter code you also
     need to patch the user interface to the Netfilter
     <code>iptables</code>. You can get the latest source code distribution
     of <code>iptables</code> from 
     <link href="http://netfilter.samba.org/">http://netfilter.samba.org/</link>. 
     The patch you need you can get from 
     <link href="http://www.racon.net/projects/bridge-fw/">http://www.racon.net/projects/bridge-fw/</link>. 
     To apply the patch you do the same thing as you did when
     patching the kernel source. Change into the root directory of the
     <code>iptables</code> source code distribution and call:
     <codeblock># patch -p1 &lt; /path/to/iptables-z.z.z-mac_dst_match.diff</codeblock>
     where <code>z.z.z</code> stands for the <code>iptables</code> version
     number here. Now configure your <code>iptables</code> source code
     properly and compile/install it. You should make sure it does not
     conflict with another installed <code>iptables</code>.
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph>
     Other software which is needed by the system but can be installed from
     precompiled software packages is:
     <unordered-list>
      <list-item>brutils - Utilities for Bridging</list-item>
      <list-item>Perl Version >= 5</list-item>
      <list-item>Internet Software Cooperation DHCP Daemon Version >= 3.0</list-item>
     </unordered-list>
    </paragraph>
   </section>

   <!-- 
     **********************************************
     *           Installing Software              *
     **********************************************
   -->

   <section heading="Installing the additional Software">
    <paragraph>
     After the system configuration is completed the Firewall Registration
     Daemon (FWREGD) can be installed. There is nothing which needs to be
     compiled and you can just unpack the FWREGD distribution to a
     directory of your choice. Usually you should put everything in
     <code>/opt/fwregd/</code>. Once you have unpacked the distribution you
     can devide the FWREGD software into two parts. One is the part which
     initalizes the Firewall and changes the configuration of the Firewall
     and the other one is observing the lease file of the DHCP server and
     initiates the change of the Firewall by calling a couple of shell
     scripts. The first part you can find underneath the directory
     <code>firewall/</code> in the root of the distribution and the second
     is available underneath <code>dhcp/</code>. Another important
     directory is <code>etc/</code> in which the configuration files are
     stored. There are also other
     directories which are not really important right now, they just
     contain patches or helper scripts to initalize system states or start
     programs. For further refernces to path names or files which are
     without a leading <code>/</code> (slash) you can assume that the path is
     relative to the root directory of the FWREGD distribution.
    </paragraph>
    <!-- 
      **********************************************
      *           Setup the Firewall               *
      **********************************************
    -->
    <section heading="Setup the Firewall">
     <paragraph>
      The concept how the Firewall Registration Deamon works is pretty
      simple. All privileges, a single machine in the network can have,
      will be combined to a set of privilege groups. These groups could be
      for example a group for client services or a group which gives the
      privilege to provide a Secure Shell (SSH) service. All Firewall rules
      belonging to one group can be summarized to one chain in the
      Firewall. To this chain can be pointed from everywhere else inside
      the chain set of the Firewall. According to the examples there could
      be chains defined called <code>CLIENT_SERVICES</code> and
      <code>SSH_SERVER</code>. Network packages reaching the Firewall and
      matching a certain criteria can be now redirected to one or more of
      these chains. In all chains the first rule that is matching is
      the exit point for the package and it will be processed (usually it
      can pass the Firewall). If there could not be a matching rule found in
      the chain of chains, then the default target is used which usually
      drops or rejects the package and do not let it pass the Firewall. All
      chains can be already created on startup of the system. The shell
      scripts which will prepare the Firewall and add all the privilege
      group chains to it are located in the directory
      <code>firewall/scripts/</code>. Because of the scripts need to be
      executed in the right order there is another directory
      <code>firewall/init.d/</code>. In this directory symbolic links to the actually
      scripts are located. This is something like the System V init style.
      The style of the names of these links is
      something like <code>script-XX-scriptname</code> where
      <code>XX</code> is a
      positive number which has a leading <code>0</code> if it is smaller
      than 10. In the Firewall initialization script, which can be found in
      <code>firewall/initFirewall.sh</code>, the links in
      <code>firewall/init.d/</code> will be executed in
      the order of the numbers in their names, starting with the lowest
      one. In these scripts all static settings to the Firewall can be
      made.
     </paragraph>
     <paragraph>
      In the default distribution there are a couple of scripts matching
      the configuration of the test system. Before you use any of these
      scripts you should adapt them to you own needs. For a detailed
      description of each script, take a look in it.
     </paragraph>
     <paragraph>
      When the Firewall Registration Daemon is running it will recognize
      when a particular machine is going online and retrieves an IP address
      from the DHCP server. 
      For that machine the FWREGD will run a script
      for each privilege group the machine is in and the script will enable
      the appropriate privileges for the machine in the Firewall. 
      For each
      privilege group the script will add an entry in the Firewall chain
      for bridging/forwarding (FORWARD) that redirects all packages
      related to the corresponding machine to the chain responsible for
      the privileges group. In that chain the privilige will be granted to
      the host.
     </paragraph>
     <paragraph>
      There is also a second script which removes all entries for a host
      from the bridging/forwarding chain of the Firewall. This script is
      called by the FWREGD when the lease time for an IP address a host is
      using has expired and the host did not refreshed it. This behavior
      makes sure that if a host is not available anymore, nobody can use
      its way through the Firewall by faking an IP or MAC address.
     </paragraph>
    </section>
    <!-- 
      **********************************************
      *           Setup the FWREGD                 *
      **********************************************
    -->
    <section heading="Setup the Firewall Registration Daemon">
     <paragraph>
      The Firewall Registration Daemon is a Perl program
      <code>dhcp/fwregd.pl</code> which can be just
      called from the command line without any arguments. It will read the
      configuration file <code>etc/bridge-fw.conf</code> and than it will
      go into daemon mode and return to the command line. In daemon mode
      it will read at first the <code>dhcpd.conf</code> file and builds an
      internal database of known hosts. The location of the
      <code>dhcpd.conf</code> is specified in the configuration file. For
      each known host the daemon will lookup an entry in the
      <code>targets.map</code> file which is also specified in the
      configuration file. The <code>targets.map</code> file contains
      information about which privileges groups should be assigned to a
      host. The names of the privileges groups are the same as the names
      of their chains in the Firewall configuration. If a host does not
      appear in the <code>targets.map</code> file a default privileges
      group will be assigned to it. This default privileges group is specified in the
      configuration file. 
     </paragraph>
     <paragraph>
      Now the daemon will start the lease file observer. The location of
      the lease file can be defined in the configuration file. The
      observer will read the lease file and parse each entry. If an entry
      belongs to a known host (that should be always the case) then there
      are three possible actions. First if the host status is
      <code>offline</code> it will be set to <code>online</code> and the
      script to enable the host in the Firewall will be executed either
      with all privileges groups defined in the <code>targets.map</code>
      file for that host or with the default privileges group. The lease
      expiration time for that lease will be stored in the internal
      database. The second possible action is if the host is already
      <code>online</code> and the lease expiration time for the lease has
      been extended. Then no status change on the host will be performed
      and the new lease expiration time will be stored in the internal
      database. The third possibility is when a host is already
      <code>online</code> and gets a new lease, that means a new IP
      address. Then the host status will be set to status
      <code>offline</code> for a short time  and directly after that to
      status <code>online</code> with the new IP address. After the lease
      file has been processed the observer will start to observe the file
      by checking each second if the status of the file has been changed.
      Ususally the DHCP server will write an entry to the lease file when a
      host refreshes its lease or requesting a new lease. If this occurs
      the observer will extract these entries and process them in the same
      way like described above. If the file is rewritten by the DHCP server
      the observer will also reopen the file an process its whole content.
     </paragraph>
     <paragraph>
      Sometimes it is also necessary to change the configuration file for
      the DHCP server <code>dhcpd.conf</code> and add or edit hosts
      information. In that case the Firewall Registration Daemon can be
      forced to update its host database by sending a SIGHUP signal to the
      process. Then it will reread the <code>dhcpd.conf</code> file and
      updates the entries in the internal host database if something has
      changed or has been added. All hosts with status <code>online</code>
      will be kept <code>online</code> except when relevant information, like
      MAC address or name has been changed. The SIGHUP signal to the daemon
      process will also cause a reread of the <code>targets.map</code>
      file. If the privileges groups an <code>online</code> host was assigned
      to have been changed, the host will be set to status <code>offline</code> and
      after that to status <code>online</code> with the new set of
      privileges.
     </paragraph>
    </section>
    <!-- 
      **********************************************
      *           Configuration File               *
      **********************************************
    -->
    <section heading="Configuration File">
     <paragraph>
      The configuration file of the Firewall Registration Daemon, the
      Firewall initialization scripts and other helper scripts can be
      found in <code>$BASE/etc</code> where <code>$BASE</code> is the path
      where you have installed the distribution, for example
      <code>/opt/fwregd</code>. The name of the configuration file is
      <code>bridge-fw.conf</code> and the style is like:
     </paragraph>
     <codeblock>
      # comment
      
      VARIABLE_NAME1="value1"
      
      # comment
      VARIABLE_NAME2="value2"</codeblock>
     <paragraph>
      The following table will show the poossible variable names, their
      meaning and which values can be assigned to them:
     </paragraph>
     <table>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>LOCAL_NETWORK</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The network address of the network which should be
        secured in dot notation with netmask.
	<example>
	 <code>LOCAL_NETWORK="192.168.10.0/24"</code><nl/>
	 or<nl/>
	 <code>LOCAL_NETWORK="141.45.0.0/255.255.0.0"</code>
	</example>
       </table-cell>
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>EXTERNAL_NETWORK</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The network address of the network which should be handled as the
        external network. <code>0.0.0.0/0</code> stands as a joker for
        every network.
	<example>
	 <code>LOCAL_NETWORK="0.0.0.0/0"</code>
	</example>
       </table-cell>
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>ROUTER_MAC</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The MAC address of the router the Firewall is place directly
        before. You can set that and avoid that packages which are not
        addressed to the router will be never sent to it. You can use
        <code>00:00:00:00:00:00</code> here as a joker which disables this
        feature.
        <example>
	 <code>ROTER_MAC="00:e0:7d:01:4d:e3"</code>
	</example>
        <bold>This has not been tested by now.</bold>
       </table-cell>
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>TRUSTED_CLIENTS</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        A list of network or host addresses which specifies the trusted
        clients in the external network. Clients listed in this list are
        able to access local network services which are enabled for trusted
        clients.
        <example>
	 You might have a local network
         <code>LOCAL_NETWORK="192.168.10.0/24"</code> which is secured from all
         other networks <code>EXTERNAL_NETWORK="0.0.0.0/0"</code> but
         should offer a special service to all clients in the whole
         <code>192.168.0.0/16</code> network. Than you should set the
         following <code>TRUSTED_CLIENTS="192.168.0.0/16"</code> and create
         a Firewall initialization script which uses this value.
        </example>
       </table-cell>
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>TRUSTED_SERVERS</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        Same thing but different. If there are trusted servers in the
        external network offering services which are usually blocked for
        local clients you can add these servers to this variable and write
        an appropriate Firewall initialization script.
        <example>
         <code>TRUSTED_SERVERS="192.168.0.0/16 10.0.0.1 10.0.0.2"</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>CLIENT_SERVICES</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        A path relative to the base path of the distribution to a file in
        the style of an <code>/etc/services</code> file. This file defines
        which services should be enabled in the
        <code>DEFAULT_CLIENT_SERVICES</code> chain in the firewall. Only
        uncommented services will be enabled.
        <example>
         <code>CLIENT_SERVICES="etc/default_client_services.conf"</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>DHCP_LEASES</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The full path to the lease file of the DHCP server. This file is
        the file where the DHCP server stores which leases it was
        given to hosts in the network.
        <example>
         <code>DHCP_LEASES="/var/state/dhcp/dhcpd.leases"</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>DHCP_CONFIG</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The full path to the configuration file of the ISC DHCP server
        which contains all hosts defined in the network.
        <example>
         <code>DHCP_CONFIG="/etc/dhcpd.conf"</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>TARGETS_MAP</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The path of the <code>targets.map</code> file 
        relative to installation directory of the distribution. This file
        maps the MAC addresses of the hosts each to a list of 
        privileges groups.
        <example>
         <code>TARGETS_MAP="etc/targets.map"</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>ENABLE_TARGET_SCRIPT</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The relative path to the script which should be executed to enable
        a privileges group for a host. Which arguments this script takes
        you will find out in the default script.
        <example>
         <code>ENABLE_TARGET_SCRIPT="firewall/enableTarget.sh"</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>DISABLE_TARGET_SCRIPT</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The relative path to the script which should be executed to disable
        a privileges group for a host. Which arguments this script takes
        you will find out in the default script.
        <example>
         <code>DISABLE_TARGET_SCRIPT="firewall/disableTarget.sh"</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>DEFAULT_TARGET</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The name of the default privileges group (chain name) 
        which should be used for
        hosts which do not have an entry in the <code>targets.map</code>
        file.
        <example>
         <code>DEFAULT_TARGET="DEFAULT_CLIENT"</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>LOGLEVEL</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The verbosity of the logging in the log file (0 - errors, 1 -
        warnings, 2 - infos, 3 - debug).
        <example>
         <code>LOGLEVEL="2"</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
      <table-row>
       <table-cell><bold>LOGFILE</bold></table-cell>
       <table-cell>
        The path to the log file.
        <example>
         <code>LOGFILE="logs/fwregd.log</code>
        </example>
       </table-cell>  
      </table-row>
     </table>
    </section>
    <section heading="Initialize the System on Bootup"/>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section heading="Known Bugs"/>
  <section heading="Things To Do"/>
 </content>
</document>

